Hello, my friends, and welcome to exercise number eighty five.
In this exercise, we are going to create the balanced binary tree and.
So I would create a new Java class called Balanced.
Binary.
Three.
You can download all the scores, source codes from the comments below from their resource folder and
the print in the Udemy course on every less and every exercise so balanced binary tree.
We start by creating the first building block, which is a class note, so class know the building block
of any tree or any data structure that supports the nodes and data.
And since we are dealing with Tree, so I need a reference to the left and reference to the right.
So
I need also a constructor for this class so know and good data.
If passed this very meter, this data could be equal to data and left, equal to right, equal to no.
OK, this is how we create a node, how we have to implement all of these nodes in the trees.
OK.
And we have dealt with this thing, and we have created it many times in the previous videos.
Now I want from you to concentrate with me a little bit since every binary tree like balance fold perfect
complete search.
And if you have any other binary three types, just remember every one, every type in these binary
trees contains its own keys.
So the key of detecting imbalance binary tree is by working for the height.
If we detect if there's a perfect binary tree, we deal with the level and depth and we have seen how
to to deal with that, how to detect and check if this perfect, complete full balance.
In the previous videos and this video we are going to to learn how to check that it is a high balance
or not, since the key of balanced binary tree is the high.
So I will create a class height here called height.
And this glass high, it contains in height
equal to zero.
Why I am doing this because I will need to use it later on in the binary tree class.
So I will create a node called the root and this root.
Will be initialized in later on in the.
Methods, so for checking, check for.
High balance
bullion.
This method returns a Boolean and the check height balance, and we start by passing the note about
the height height,
and we start by checking for empty, so empty three or not, if fraud equal equal to none.
Then hide the tide.
But getting the height equal to zero and return to OK.
Now.
I need to create an instance from the high, so height left a high.
Left tied.
Equal to new height.
And the height right height equal to a new height,
and we create a boolean and equal to check height balance, and we passed the route left and we passed
the left height.
OK, so we have used this method again by using the recursion.
So you see the recursion symbol, we are using the recursion symbol until reaching for root equal to
null, then height equal to zero and return.
We are checking by passing the left route, the left sub three, and we passed the left side and again
creating a Boolean that are Boolean
are equal to check height, balance and the route to right right height.
And this is for left and right.
We start by using the recursion.
We have used this method again and again to check the height balance and returning the result left and
right.
If they are balanced or not, and we have seen in the previous video in the lecture that in order to
have balance the left and balanced right.
So we get a balanced binary tree.
So we are checking the sub three of the main three, the left and the right, storing that result in
left and and off.
Now, let's create left tight, left tight end.
It is calculated by creating left heights equal to left.
Left left, Hyde is equal to left Hyde, though it.
It works with Britain who are going to make here and left height equal to left height, height and the
right height.
Right height.
I will add that is equal to ride height height.
OK.
We are getting that iPad and the left high, no checking if height dot high equal to.
Left height and greater than.
Greater than this is very important to greater than ride height with Edge.
See, we are comparing the integers I have added intentionally in your etch a second etch here in order
to check for this comparison is equal.
If left height greater than the right height, then it is equal to the left high.
Otherwise, it will be equal to that high.
This is a very important check and we add +1 for it.
So the height assigned the height is equal either to the left, if left the greater than right or to
the right, if the left is less than the right plus one.
OK.
It's very important now we check also to the left.
I told you that the core the that the key in this balanced minority is checking the left side and the
right time, OK, and working with heights, so the right height greater than or equal to two or the
difference.
This is we are checking the difference.
I told you that the difference between the left side and the right type greater than to it where it
falls or the right height minus the left high, greater than or equal to two, then return false.
So it is not a balanced three else, it will return and that is of of l and off.
So if L, which is Boolean using the check type balance, if it is balanced and the right balance left
is true and right is true.
So it will be true.
Otherwise, if any of the L or R is false, then it would return false.
So we have learned in this balanced by industry to check if the left binary tree left sub three is balanced
and the right tree is balanced, then it will return through and we check if the height of the left
the tree is less than the right tree or both.
Why not?
More than one, it will return through.
Otherwise it will return false.
So these are the two conditions that we have worked on then.
Let's test our code now and called Method.
Main method.
Hi.
This is a new class of third class hide you object of our home and balanced binary tree called the three
equal to you.
I was buying it to be.
New height makes static.
And we start implementing the three, so 3DR put equal to and, you know, we are adding the notes here
and three the truth, though it left equal to new known two three.
The true thought right.
Equal to new No.
Three.
Three the through the left, the left vehicle from, you know, four and three door through the left
thought it might be equal to you, you know it.
And we insert five OK, no alt plus enter to see the arrows.
Make no static.
And no, it has been become static.
OK, now let's see
if.
If three, though, check height, balance three, the truth and the truth.
And we passed the height, then we see that it is a system that our to print and that tree is balanced.
Otherwise it will become that three is not balanced.
OK,
let's run and see.
That three is sorry, I have run the previous one.
Every time I have this letter, the three is balanced, OK?
Because if we drove this through this map or this three, it would give us a balance.
Three having the same, the same.
The difference between the height of the left and the right trees would be not more than one.
And we have checked that the balance sub three to the left is balanced and the left and the right sub
three is balanced to the right game.
So everything is working fine.
We have to condition to work for them.
We are checking the balance two that both sub trees and we have checked that the height is not more
than what.
OK, so this is balanced by three.
I hope you build from our videos and I am waiting for your suggestions, your questions, your answers
to their asking questions and videos and exercises.
And I want from you to support us on Udemy.
A.